Guide to Samuel Hollyer's Old New York Views 1901-1912, undated PR 86
New-York Historical Society
Samuel Hollyer's Old New York Views
1901-1912, undated
New-York Historical Society
PR 86
0.42 Linear feet (1 box)
Samuel Hollyer's Old New York views were created at the turn of the twentieth century to recall sites and scenes in the city and the Hudson River Valley that had largely disappeared in the previous three centuries. The images are of historically important sites, houses, taverns, churches, forts, theaters, and public buildings.
Provenance
The collection has been compiled from gifts from various donors.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to thirty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. See guidelines in Print Room for details.
Biographical Note
Samuel Hollyer (1826-1919) was born in London, England, where he was trained as an engraver by the brothers Edward and William Finden. He came to the United States in 1851, and worked for various New York book publishers until 1860 when he returned to England to live.
Six years later, Hollyer came back to America, settling in Hudson Heights, near Guttenberg, New Jersey, a small community across the Hudson River from Manhattan. He commuted daily to his studio in New York, where he created line and stipple engravings, mezzotints, and etchings for various publications and print collectors. Bookplates were one of his specialties, as were portraits of literary celebrities.
Samuel Hollyer died in New York in December 1919, at the age of 93. His obituary in the New York Times described him as "one of the last, if not the very last, of the old school of line engravers."
Scope and Content Note
Samuel Hollyer's Old New York views were created at the turn of the twentieth century to recall sites and scenes in the city and the Hudson River Valley that had largely disappeared in the previous three centuries. It is unknown by what system and in what quantity Hollyer issued his prints, but they were collected by antiquarians and prominent New Yorkers including J. Clarence Davies, who owned 141 Old New York prints bound into three volumes with letterpress printed title and text pages. The Davies volumes are in the collection of the Museum of the City of New York (Acc. No. 29.100.302 A-C, each with a Davies bookplate by Hollyer), and it is that set that was used to assign the numbers used to arrange the prints in PR 086. The New-York Historical Society prints are disbound and have only the set of title and text pages from volume I (prints 1 through 65). The N-YHS Volume I originals and photocopies, made from the Davies volumes, of the texts in Volumes II and III are filed before the corresponding prints.
The collection is divided into three series, one each for the bound volumes described above. Thereunder, prints in each volume are arranged in an alphabetical order and numbered according to that order. The numbering system continues throughout the three volumes, but each volume is individually alphabetically arranged.
The prints are titled in Hollyer's hand in the margin, and are numbered according to the text pages, which give a paragraph-long description of the location and importance of each site. Many prints have a number written in a different hand in pencil in the lower right corner; this number does not always correspond to the number assigned to the print in the text. Another hand has annotated some of the titles and dates given as that contemporary to the view. These annotations appear in the container list in brackets. Titles in the container list are taken from the published text.
Duplicate prints exist for about twenty percent of the prints, and are housed in a folder at the end of the numerical run of prints.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into three series, one each for the bound volumes described above. Thereunder, prints in each volume are arranged in an alphabetical order.
Missing Title
Series I. Old New York, Volume I
Series II. Old New York, Volume II
Series III. Old New York, Volume III
Architecture, Domestic -- New York (State) -- New York.; Church buildings -- New York (State) -- New York.; Engravings (prints); New York (N.Y.) -- Buildings, structures, etc.; Theaters -- New York (State) -- New York.; New York (N.Y.) -- Pictorial works.; Hollyer, Samuel, 1826-1919
- Series I: Old New York, Volume I
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I. Volume I holds sixty-five prints engraved by Hollyer between 1901 and 1905, and issued in a set under the title OLD NEW YORK/VIEWS/BY/S. HOLLYER/New York, 1905. The images are of historically important sites, houses, taverns, forts, theaters, and public buildings dating from 1653 (the Water Gate, a gate and blockhouse in lower Manhattan) to 1899 (the Dewey Arch). Over half of the images represent 19th-century sites, with most of the remainder from the 18th century. Castle Garden, Fraunces' Tavern, and the Tombs Prison are pictured in this series.
  Prints in Series I are arranged by numbers in the order established by the text issued with the prints.
  - Text issued with Volume I, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1. Andre's Prison, 1777, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 2. Audubon Estate, 1852, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 3. Belvedere Club, 1794, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 4. Bowery Theatre, 1826, [1903] (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 5. Broadway Theatre, 1859, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 6. Buckhorn Tavern (22nd St. & Bdy), 1812, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 7. Broad St. & Federal Hall, 1798 [1789], undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 8. Burn's Coffee House (front view), 1760, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 9. Burn's Coffee House (rear), 1760, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 10. Bowling Green, 1830, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 11. Burnham's Hotel, Bloomingdale Road, 1852, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 12. Castle Garden, 1852, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 13. Cato's Inn - Old Post Road, 1715, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 14. Catherine Market, 1850, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 15. City Hall, 1852, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 16. City Hall & Park, 1849, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 17. Collect Pond, 1802, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 18. Croton Aquaduct [sic], 1850, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 19. Dewey Arch, 1899, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 20. Dutch Cottages, Beaver St., 1679, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 21. De Wint House (Tappan), 1700, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 22. First Hotel, New Amsterdam, 1642, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 23. First Merchants' Exchange, 1790, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 24. Fort Fish (McGowan's Pass), 1814, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 25. Fraunces' Tavern, 1777, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 26. Fly Market, 1816, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 27. Franklin Market, 1820, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 28. Gov. Geo. Clinton's House - Pearl St. [1856], 1903 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 29. Old Gotham Inn - Bowery, 1850, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 30. Old Golden Tavern, 1792, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 31. Hamilton Grange, 1802, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 32. Hell Gate, 1775, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 33. John St. Theatre, 1767, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 34. Jumel Mansion, 1810, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 35. Little Church round the corner built 1849, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 36. Madison Cottage, 23rd St. & Bdy, 1852, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 37. McComb's Dam Bridge, 1850, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 38. No. 1 Broadway - Washington Hotel, 1851, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 39. New York Tattersall's, 1840, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 40. Niblo's Garden, rear view, 1820, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 41. New Amsterdam, 1664, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 42. Old Brewery, Five Points, 1852, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 43. Old Blue Bell Tavern, Kingsbridge, 1785, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 44. Old Bull's Head Tavern, 1762, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 45. Park Theatre, 1831, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 46. Poe's Cottage, Fordham, 1852, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 47. Rip Van Dam Church, 1729, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 48. Peter Stuyvesant's Town House, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 49. Peter Stuyvesant's Country House, 14th St., 1658, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 50. State St., and Battery Park, 1852, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 51. Strawberry Hill Hotel (now Woodlawn), 1852, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 52. Shakespeare Tavern, 1820, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 53. St. George's Church - Beekman St., 1752, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 54. St. John's Church, 1829, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 55. St. Luke's Church, 1850, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 56. Tombs Prison, 1850, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 57. Trinity Church, 1791, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 58. Tontine Coffee House, 1796, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 59. Turtle Bay - East River [1853], 1904 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 60. U.S. Bank & Insurance Offices, 1798, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 61. Old Vandenheuvel Mansion, 1759, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 62. Van Rensselaer's Manor House, 1680, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 63. Van Cortland Manor House, 1820, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 64. Water Gate, 1653, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 65. Washington's House, Cherry Street, 1777, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series II. Old New York, Volume II
  Series II. Volume II holds forty more engravings of similar scenes as those found in Volume I. The prints are numbered 66 through 110 and issued under a 1909 title page. The prints were made between 1905 and 1908, and capture historic places dating from 1626 (Fort Amsterdam) to 1859 (Washington Market). Again, most of the images are of places prominent in the 19th century, and include street scenes as well as houses, hotels, taverns, schools, churches, etc. Columbia College, the College of the City of New York, Bellevue Hospital, and Washington Market are prominent buildings pictured in this series. The prints have been arranged by print numbers found in the text pages of MCNY's Davies set.
  Prints in series II are arranged by their numbers, which follows the order established by the text issued with the prints. Print titles in brackets and in italic are part of the original set but are not represented in this collection.
  - Copy of text issued with Volume II, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 66. Apthorpe Mansion, 1790, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 67. [Astor House, 1831], undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 68. Bellevue Hospital, 1830, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 69. Broad Street, 1659, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 70. Bull's Head [Hotel] (24th St & 3rd Ave.), 1830, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 71. City Hotel, 1831, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 72. Columbia College, 1828, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 73. College of the City of New York, 1820 [1848], 1906 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 74. [Van] De Voor Farm, 1698, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 75. Eden Farm, 1797, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 76. First French Church, 1688 [ca. 1750], 1905 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 77. First Garden Street Church, 1693, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 78. First Brick Presbyterian Church, 1768, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 79. [First Trip of Fulton's Steamboat 1807] (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 80. First Watch House in NY, 1700, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 81. Fort Amsterdam [1626], 1908 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 82. Fort George, 1750, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 83. Fort Lafayette, 1850, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 84. Old Fulton Ferry, 1746, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 85. Government House, 1790, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 86. Gouverneur Morris' House, 1798, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 87. [House in Twenty-third Street] Residence of Mayor Tieman'sFather (22nd St.), 1850, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 88. Hunt's Mansion, 1770 [1790], 1906 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 89. Jefferson Market [1857], 1907 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 90. Kingsbridge Road (near Dykeman's Farm), 1855, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 91. New York City Reservoir, 1829, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 92. No. 1 Strand, 1690, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 93. North Church Fulton [1769], 1906 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 94. North Fort and U.S. Frigate Constitution, 1832, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 95. [Old Ferry House, Broad Street, 1700] (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 96. Old Grapevine Inn [Tavern}, 1851, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 97. Old National Theatre, 1839, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 98. Old Post Office, 1850, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 99. Phillipse Manor House (Yonkers), 1855, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 100. [Riker Estate, 1830] (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 101. Rotunda, 1816, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 102. [Shot Tower, 1836] (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 103. [Shot Tower - Centre Street, 1858] (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 104. Theological Seminary, 1833, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 105. Union Square & Broadway, 1849, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 106. Van Nest House, 1830, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 107. Wall Street, 1825, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 108. Walton House, 1784, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 109. Washington Market, 1859, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 110. New York Harbor & Yacht Fancy, 1717, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Series III: Old New York, Volume III
  Series III. Volume III contains thirty-one more plates, dating in history from 1609 (The Half Moon) to 1888 (The Statue of Liberty), created by Hollyer between 1908 and 1910. The prints are numbered 111 through 141 and were issued under a 1912 title page. This series contains more landscape type views than the other two, including views of the East River and lower Manhattan. The New-York Historical Society building of 1851 is shown. The prints have been arranged by print numbers found in the text pages of MCNY's Davies set.
  Prints in series III are arranged by their numbers, which follows the order established by the text issued with the prints. Print titles in brackets and in italic are part of the original set but are not represented in this collection.
  - Copy of text issued with Volume III, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 111. American Museum, City Hall Park, 1825, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 112. [Barnum's Museum, 1853] (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 113. [Burton's Theatre, 1848] (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 114. Cottages on John Jacob Astor's Farm, 1836, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 115. Clermont Manor House, 1820, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 116. Contoit's Garden (Broadway), 1830, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 117. Earliest Library in New York, 1795, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 118. East River from Riker's Island, 1798, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 119. [Fulton Market, 1850] (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 120. The Half Moon, 1609, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 121. [Havemeyer Mansion, 1850] (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 122. House of Refuge (Madison Square), 1826, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 123. King's Bridge, 1856, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 124. Knickerbocker Cottage, 1851, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 125. Livingston Manor House, 1870, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 126. Lower Market, 1720, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 127. Lydig House & Mill on the Bronx, 1820, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 128. Masonic Hall, Broadway, 1828, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 129. New York Historical Society, 1851, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 130. New York Society Library, 1856, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 131. [No. 7 State Street, 1850] (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 132. [Novum Amsterdam, 1667] (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 133. Old Cottages in Frankfort St., 1859, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 134. [Revenue Office, 1855] (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 135. [Sleepy Hollow Church] Old Dutch Church (Tarrytown), 1850, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 136. Statue of Liberty, 1888 [1886], 1910 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 137. Stewart Mansion, 1870 [1860], 1909 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 138. [View of New York from] Old dueling ground, Weehawaken, 1804 [1852], 1910 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 139. [House] Where Poe wrote the Raven, 1860 [1844], 1909 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 140. Washington's Headquarters (Newburgh), 1777 [1860], 1909 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 141. Yonkers, from Sketch made in 1784, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 12)